{"tossups":[{"question":"A musician named after this person spelled out “LSD” over and over again using the initial letters of the words in a verse from the song “The Greatest Pac-Man Victory in History.” In one story, this person is born unable to speak, but is given the power of speech by Isis as a reward for giving her directions. The Pudding published a token analysis of lyrics which found that a rapper named after this person had the largest (*) vocabulary of any of the analyzed rappers; in that rapper’s stage name, this person’s name is followed by “rock.” The idea that this author was African was popularized by Planudes’s [plah-NOO-daze’s] false etymology deriving his name from “Ethiopia.” The phrases “sour grapes” and “cry wolf” come from stories by, for 10 points, what ancient Greek author of fables?","formatted_answer":"<b><u>Aesop<\/b><\/u> [or <b><u>Aisopos<\/b><\/u>; accept <b><u>Aesop<\/b><\/u> Rock]","answer":"<b><u>Aesop<\/b><\/u> [or <b><u>Aisopos<\/b><\/u>; accept <b><u>Aesop<\/b><\/u> Rock]","category":"Trash","subcategory":"Trash","packetNumber":8,"questionNumber":1},{"question":"This person’s daughter Alicia, who was able to visualize four-dimensional space, coined the word “polytope” for a solid in four or more dimensions. Abramowitz and Stegun introduced a persistent typo in the name of this person’s “rule,” which gives a method of numerical integration. This professor at Queen’s College Cork coined the phrase “universe of discourse” in the book The (*) Laws of Thought. Charles Sanders Peirce [purse] helped popularize an adjective derived from this man’s name, which describes a “satisfiability problem” in computer science and a type of function that can be implemented by a logic gate. For 10 points, what mathematician lends his name to expressions that evaluate to either true or false?","formatted_answer":"George <b><u>Boole<\/b><\/u> [accept Mary Everest <b><u>Boole<\/b><\/u> before “rule”] (Abramowitz and Stegun accidentally wrote “Boole’s rule” as “Bode’s rule.”)","answer":"George <b><u>Boole<\/b><\/u> [accept Mary Everest <b><u>Boole<\/b><\/u> before “rule”] (Abramowitz and Stegun accidentally wrote “Boole’s rule” as “Bode’s rule.”)","category":"Philosophy","subcategory":"Philosophy","packetNumber":8,"questionNumber":2},{"question":"This word is usually thought to have arisen from the loss of the final “-el” of an Old English word meaning “hermaphrodite.” Noah Webster thought this word came from the identically-spelled Persian word with the same meaning, but the similarity turns out to be a coincidence. This adjective and its alphabetically-later opposite are two of the extremely small number of English (*) suppletive [suh-PLEE-tiv] adjectives. This word has a positive valence in the title of a song about people who “live fast” and  “die young,” recorded by M.I.A [M-I-A]. The Mandinka language may be the source of the use of this word to mean its opposite in African-American Vernacular English, as well as the idiom that combines this word with “mouth.” For 10 points, name this adjective whose comparative form is “worse.”","formatted_answer":"<b><u>bad<\/b><\/u> [accept “<b><u>Bad<\/b><\/u> Girls”] (A suppletive adjective is one whose comparative and superlative forms are not cognate with it, such as “worse” and “worst” for “bad.”)","answer":"<b><u>bad<\/b><\/u> [accept “<b><u>Bad<\/b><\/u> Girls”] (A suppletive adjective is one whose comparative and superlative forms are not cognate with it, such as “worse” and “worst” for “bad.”)","category":"History","subcategory":"World History","packetNumber":8,"questionNumber":3},{"question":"Aptly, “neologize” is one of the many words coined by this person, who introduced the word “catenary” in a letter about bridge construction written to a friend. Procedures for dealing with “disorderly words” are outlined in this person’s Manual of Parliamentary Practice. Out of a desire to select “the very words only of Jesus,” this person used a razor and (*) glue to cut and paste sections of the New Testament. This man introduced the word “pedicure” to English after his time in Paris, where he served as the second U.S. Minister to France. Congress extensively debated the wording of a text drafted by the Committee of Five whose first draft was written by this man. For 10 points, name this president who wrote the Declaration of Independence.","formatted_answer":"Thomas <b><u>Jefferson<\/b><\/u>","answer":"Thomas <b><u>Jefferson<\/b><\/u>","category":"Fine Arts","subcategory":"Other Fine Arts","packetNumber":8,"questionNumber":4},{"question":"The word “bingerle” is used with this meaning in some of the letters of Alexander II of Russia. In reference to an incident involving Mary Kenny, Private Eye magazine often used the phrase “Ugandan discussions” with this meaning. This is the meaning of the archaic word “swiving.” In Remembrance of Things Past, Charles Swann gives this meaning to the word (*) “cattleya” [CAT-lee-uh], which is the name of a type of orchid. In a tale from the Decameron, Rustico convinces Alibech that this is the meaning of the phrase “putting the Devil back in Hell.” This is the meaning of “knowing” in the biblical sense of the word. For 10 points, Othello uses the phrase “making the beast with two backs” as a euphemism for what activity?","formatted_answer":"having <b><u>sex<\/b><\/u>ual intercourse [accept synonyms, which are too numerous to list]","answer":"having <b><u>sex<\/b><\/u>ual intercourse [accept synonyms, which are too numerous to list]","category":"Science","subcategory":"Chemistry","packetNumber":8,"questionNumber":5},{"question":"A collection of “the five hundred essential” words of this type was translated by Kris Young Kondo and William J. Higginson, the latter of whom wrote a 1996 book that lists these words with examples of their usage. Grace Lavery’s [LAV-uh-ree’s] book Quaint, Exquisite highlights the lack of these words in a poem inspired by “The Blessed Damozel,” and argues that “petals” serves as a psychic equivalent of this type of word in Ezra Pound’s “In a (*) Station of the Metro.” These words are listed along with examples of their usage in almanac-like books called saijiki [sye-jee-kee]. Kawazu [kah-wah-zoo], meaning “frog,” serves as this type of word in a Matsuo Basho poem that uses ya [yah] as a “cutting word.” For 10 points, name these words used in haiku that are associated with a particular time of year.","formatted_answer":"<b><u>season<\/b><\/u> words [or <b><u>kigo<\/b><\/u>]","answer":"<b><u>season<\/b><\/u> words [or <b><u>kigo<\/b><\/u>]","category":"Literature","subcategory":"World Literature","packetNumber":8,"questionNumber":6},{"question":"A character played by this actor is told “you’re acting like a real C-word right now” by a man who then clarifies “that’s right, a Cranky Sue.” That character played by this actor is bummed out by the word “lovers” unless it’s between the word “meat” and “pizza.” A show created by this actor popularized the term EGOT [EE-got] with a fourth-season arc in which a character tries to (*) earn an EGOT after finding a diamond-encrusted EGOT necklace. In a screenplay by this actor, Gretchen Wieners tries to make the slang term “fetch” happen. “Blërg” [blurg] is both the favorite Ikea furniture line of and a common exclamation used by this actor’s character of Liz Lemon. For 10 points, the Mean Girls screenplay is by what creator and star of 30 Rock?","formatted_answer":"Tina <b><u>Fey<\/b><\/u> [or Elizabeth Stamatina <b><u>Fey<\/b><\/u>]","answer":"Tina <b><u>Fey<\/b><\/u> [or Elizabeth Stamatina <b><u>Fey<\/b><\/u>]","category":"Fine Arts","subcategory":"Other Fine Arts","packetNumber":8,"questionNumber":7},{"question":"Roberto Navigli’s survey of this task identifies the knowledge acquisition bottleneck as one of its major hurdles. A bootstrapping algorithm for this task that uses a decision list base classifier is called the Yarowsky algorithm. A series of evaluations of algorithms for performing this task is the predecessor of the current SemEval [sem-ee-val] series, which includes a wider variety of tasks. The inventory needed for this task is typically derived from (*) WordNet, though WordNet’s distinctions are sometimes considered too fine-grained to be useful. Margaret Masterman used Roget’s Thesaurus in an early attempt at tackling this task. For 10 points, name this task of identifying what meaning of a word is used in a particular sentence.","formatted_answer":"word-sense <b><u>disambiguation<\/b><\/u> [or <b><u>WSD<\/b><\/u>; or lexical <b><u>disambiguation<\/b><\/u>]","answer":"word-sense <b><u>disambiguation<\/b><\/u> [or <b><u>WSD<\/b><\/u>; or lexical <b><u>disambiguation<\/b><\/u>]","category":"Science","subcategory":"Other Science","packetNumber":8,"questionNumber":8},{"question":"A pun on these two words appears at the end of the line beginning “But swear by thyself” in John Donne’s “A Hymn to God the Father.” Mark Schwartzberg argues that a pun on these words in Shakespeare’s “Full many a glorious morning have I seen” references a personal tragedy that took place in 1596. These homophones are punned on in Hamlet’s response to Claudius’s question “How is it that the clouds still hang on you?” A pun on these two words is followed by the observation that the “clouds that (*) lour’d upon our house” are now “in the deep bosom of the ocean.” These words are punned on in the second line of Richard III, following “Now is the winter of our discontent.” For 10 points, name these words that can fill in the blank in the line “Made glorious summer by this [blank] of York.”","formatted_answer":"<b><u>son<\/b><\/u> and <b><u>sun<\/b><\/u> (Schwartzberg argues that “Full many a glorious morning have I seen” references the death of Shakespeare’s son Hamnet.)","answer":"<b><u>son<\/b><\/u> and <b><u>sun<\/b><\/u> (Schwartzberg argues that “Full many a glorious morning have I seen” references the death of Shakespeare’s son Hamnet.)","category":"Social Science","subcategory":"Social Science","packetNumber":8,"questionNumber":9},{"question":"A treaty defining this word was first successfully put into practice in the 1998 case of Jean-Paul Akayesu; the U.S. signed that treaty in 1988, largely thanks to the efforts of William Proxmire. A word patterned on this word but starting with the prefix “ethno-” was coined by Robert Jaulin [zhoh-LEN]. Raphael (*) Lemkin’s coinage of this word is cited in a 2019 lawsuit filed by The Gambia. This word is the first of the four main terms defined in the Rome Statute. The much-discussed phrase “in whole or in part” is used in a U.N. convention named for this word. In 2021, Antony Blinken stated that the CCP’s actions in Xinjiang [shin-j’yong] could be described by this word. For 10 points, name this word for the systematic destruction of a people.","formatted_answer":"<b><u>genocide<\/b><\/u>","answer":"<b><u>genocide<\/b><\/u>","category":"Social Science","subcategory":"Social Science","packetNumber":8,"questionNumber":10},{"question":"In 2020, several record-breaking examples of these texts in Latin were created by Eric Tentarelli. The most famous text of this type, whose second word is a hapax legomenon [HAP-ax luh-GOM-uh-non] that has been interpreted as a name for Harpocrates [har-POCK-ruh-teez], can be translated as a sentence about a farmer who uses the wheels of a plow for work. That one of these texts can be rearranged to form a Greek cross made of the word (*) “Paternoster” intersecting itself, with two A’s and two O’s left over. The title of the film Tenet is a reference to a palindromic one of these texts that was found in the ruins of Pompeii and starts with the word “sator.” For 10 points, name these texts consisting of words arranged horizontally and vertically in an n-by-n grid.","formatted_answer":"<b><u>word square<\/b><\/u>s [accept <b><u>magic square<\/b><\/u>s; prompt on <u>acrostic<\/u>s; reject “crosswords”]","answer":"<b><u>word square<\/b><\/u>s [accept <b><u>magic square<\/b><\/u>s; prompt on acrostics; reject “crosswords”]","category":"Mythology","subcategory":"Mythology","packetNumber":8,"questionNumber":11},{"question":"A dialect named for this historical region uses a word meaning “the scrotum of a housefly” as a humorous unit of measurement. A diminutive word that may mean “little sparrow” in this region’s dialect refers to the local noodle dish “Spätzle” [SHPETZ-luh]. A surname literally meaning someone from this region is possessed by a man who pioneered discount sales of equity securities in the 1970s. A phrase translating as (*) “lick me on the arse” is euphemistically known as this region’s “salute,” because it was used by Götz von Berlichingen [guhts fawn bair-LEKH-ing-in] when a league named after this region invited him to surrender. This region is named after an alternate name for the Alemanni. For 10 points, name this German region which is referenced by the surnames “Svevo” [S’VAY-voh] and “Schwab” [shwob].","formatted_answer":"<b><u>Swabia<\/b><\/u> [or <b><u>Schwaben<\/b><\/u>; accept <b><u>Swabia<\/b><\/u>n salute; prompt on <u>Alemannia<\/u> before “equity”]","answer":"<b><u>Swabia<\/b><\/u> [or <b><u>Schwaben<\/b><\/u>; accept <b><u>Swabia<\/b><\/u>n salute; prompt on Alemannia before “equity”]","category":"Literature","subcategory":"European Literature","packetNumber":8,"questionNumber":12},{"question":"The “demise” of the debate over the meaning of this word is the subject of a Larry Laudan [“louden”] paper which notes that “apodictic [ap-oh-DIK-tik] certainty” was the key aspect of Aristotle’s definition of this word. The debate over the meaning of this word inspired Thomas F. Gieryn [GAIR-in] to coin the term “boundary-work.” The attempt to develop a unified “language of [this term]” in the Aufbau [OWF-bow] by Rudolf (*) Carnap is criticized in the book Conjectures and Refutations. The demarcation problem is the problem of distinguishing this word from similar words starting with the prefixes “non-” and “pseudo-.” For 10 points, name this word describing a discipline which, according to Karl Popper, should be based on the criterion of falsifiability.","formatted_answer":"<b><u>science<\/b><\/u> [or <b><u>scientific<\/b><\/u>; or <b><u>scientist<\/b><\/u>]","answer":"<b><u>science<\/b><\/u> [or <b><u>scientific<\/b><\/u>; or <b><u>scientist<\/b><\/u>]","category":"Philosophy","subcategory":"Philosophy","packetNumber":8,"questionNumber":13},{"question":"In a painting by this artist, the archangel Michael’s buckler displays the mysterious words “Adoravi tetgrammathon agla” [ah-doh-RAH-vee tet-GRAM-uh-tahn AH-glah], the last of which also appears on floor tiles in another painting by this artist. In a painting by this artist, a quote from the Book of Wisdom saying “she is more beautiful than the sun” is embroidered on Mary’s robe. In an Annunciation by this artist, the words “ecce ancilla Domini” [ET-chay on-CHEEL-lah DOH-mee-nee] are written (*) upside-down. This artist’s signature often includes a phrase meaning “as I can” that puns on this artist’s name. Words meaning “music in praise of God” accompany the depiction of angels playing music in a polyptych [PAH-lip-tik] by this artist in which inscriptions appear over the heads of God, Mary, and John the Baptist in the center. For 10 points, name this painter of the Ghent Altarpiece.","formatted_answer":"Jan <b><u>van Eyck<\/b><\/u>","answer":"Jan <b><u>van Eyck<\/b><\/u>","category":"Fine Arts","subcategory":"Visual Fine Arts","packetNumber":8,"questionNumber":14},{"question":"A theory whose name starts with this prefix posited that the body produces tiny particles called gemmules [JEM-yoolz] that migrate to the gonads. Wilhelm Johannsen removed this prefix from a word coined by Hugo de Vries to create the word “gene.” Charles Darwin proposed a theory of heredity whose name combines this prefix with the word “genesis.” Fred Hoyle and Svante (*) Arrhenius [SVAHN-teh ah-REE-nee-us] espoused another theory whose name starts with this prefix, positing that life on Earth originated from molecules from outer space. This prefix precedes “thalassa” [thuh-LASS-uh] in the name of an ocean that formerly surrounded a structure from the Paleozoic and Mesozoic eras whose name starts with this prefix. For 10 points, what Greek prefix meaning “all” precedes “gaea” [JEE-uh] in the name of a supercontinent?","formatted_answer":"<b><u>pan-<\/b><\/u> [accept <b><u>pangenesis<\/b><\/u>; accept <b><u>pangene<\/b><\/u>; accept <b><u>panspermia<\/b><\/u>; accept <b><u>Panthalassa<\/b><\/u>; accept <b><u>Pangaea<\/b><\/u>]","answer":"<b><u>pan-<\/b><\/u> [accept <b><u>pangenesis<\/b><\/u>; accept <b><u>pangene<\/b><\/u>; accept <b><u>panspermia<\/b><\/u>; accept <b><u>Panthalassa<\/b><\/u>; accept <b><u>Pangaea<\/b><\/u>]","category":"Science","subcategory":"Biology","packetNumber":8,"questionNumber":15},{"question":"A song whose title uses a stylized spelling of this word includes the line “I was your Butch, and you were touched,” and was released as a single from the album Radio City by Big Star. This word is spelled creatively in the title of a 2022 Amazon Prime reality show about a singer recruiting backup dancers. A 2022 song titled for a stylized spelling of this word was re-released with the line (*) “Hold me back” replacing a lyric that included an ableist slur. A song whose title uses a stylized spelling of this word describes “fine, fresh, fierce” people who “got it on lock.” This word is spelled creatively in the name of a movement that was started in Olympia, Washington by bands like Bratmobile and Bikini Kill. For 10 points, name this word that follows “California” in a Katy Perry song title.","formatted_answer":"<b><u>girl<\/b><\/u>s","answer":"<b><u>girl<\/b><\/u>s","category":"History","subcategory":"World History","packetNumber":8,"questionNumber":16},{"question":"One name for this empire is the source of the Chinese name Anxi [ahn-shee], is abbreviated as “An” in the names of the missionaries from this empire who were the first people to translate Indian Buddhist texts into Chinese. Most borrowings in classical Armenian came from a now-extinct language named for this empire. An early use of the word “philhellene” [fil-HEL-een], meaning “lover of the Greeks,” was on the coins of this empire’s (*) Mithridates I [mith-rih-DAY-teez the first], who was descended from the 3rd-century BC founder after whom this empire is sometimes named. A technique in which this empire’s horse archers would fire backwards at pursuing enemies may be the origin of the phrase “parting shot.” For 10 points, name this Persian empire between the Seleucids [suh-LOO-sidz] and the Sassanids [SASS-uh-nidz].","formatted_answer":"<b><u>Parthia<\/b><\/u>n Empire [or <b><u>Arsacid<\/b><\/u> Empire]","answer":"<b><u>Parthia<\/b><\/u>n Empire [or <b><u>Arsacid<\/b><\/u> Empire]","category":"History","subcategory":"Ancient History","packetNumber":8,"questionNumber":17},{"question":"This Greek word is coincidentally spelled the same as an Old Norse word that is combined with hjalmr [H’YAL-moor] in the name of a terrifying helmet known as the “Helm of Awe” in English. In Egyptology, this word can refer to a collar-like necklace that depicts the head of a deity, such as the one that Bast is often shown carrying. This word, which can mean “violent windstorm,” denotes an object whose shaking causes Mount (*) Ida to shake. This word likely derives from a word for “goat” and is often interpreted as referring to a goatskin coat that depicts the head of Medusa in the center. Figuratively, this word can mean “auspices” [OSS-puh-sizz] or “patronage.” For 10 points, name this Greek word referring to a shield carried by Athena.","formatted_answer":"<b><u>aegis<\/b><\/u> [EE-jiss]","answer":"<b><u>aegis<\/b><\/u> [EE-jiss]","category":"History","subcategory":"Ancient History","packetNumber":8,"questionNumber":18},{"question":"When these things have names that look or sound alike, they are referred to by the acronym LASA [L-A-S-A]. To avoid confusion, the names of these things are often written using tall-man lettering. The USAN [U-S-A-N] Council assigns “United States Adopted Names” to these things. A publication informally known as the Stem Book lists stems used in (*) INNs [I-N-N’s], which are common names for these things. A largely obsolete two-word Latin phrase starting with materia refers to the body of knowledge about these things. Many countries have national formularies that list the names of these things. Suffixes like “-tinib” [tin-IB] and “-azepam” [AZ-uh-pam] are used in the names of, for 10 points, what things that have proprietary names like Tylenol?","formatted_answer":"<b><u>drug<\/b><\/u>s [or <b><u>pharmaceutical<\/b><\/u>s; or <b><u>medication<\/b><\/u>s; or <b><u>medicine<\/b><\/u>s]","answer":"<b><u>drug<\/b><\/u>s [or <b><u>pharmaceutical<\/b><\/u>s; or <b><u>medication<\/b><\/u>s; or <b><u>medicine<\/b><\/u>s]","category":"Social Science","subcategory":"Social Science","packetNumber":8,"questionNumber":19},{"question":"Improper pronunciations of this word are described by terms like chatufa [hah-too-FAH], ketufa [keh-too-FAH], and yetoma [yeh-toh-MAH], meaning “snatched,” “cut,” and “orphaned.” After murdering Duncan, Macbeth describes how this word “stuck in my throat” when he tried to speak it. The Talmud teaches that this word is an acronym for a phrase meaning (*) “God, faithful king.” Though this word has been borrowed unaltered into many languages, it is sometimes translated as ainsi soit-il [en-see swah-TEEL] in Cajun French. This word is used in response to a berakhah [brah-HAH], or a formula of blessing. Some esotericists falsely claim that this word comes from the name of an Egyptian god who was fused with Ra. For 10 points, name this word used at the end of Christian prayers.","formatted_answer":"<b><u>amen<\/b><\/u>","answer":"<b><u>amen<\/b><\/u>","category":"Religion","subcategory":"Religion","packetNumber":8,"questionNumber":20}],"bonuses":[]}
